Finding Aid for Housing Public Affairs (University of Michigan) records, 1965-2006
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Housing Public Affairs (University of Michigan) records 1965-2006, 1980-2000
University of Michigan. Housing Public Affairs.
6 linear feet
2008158 Bimu 2
The University of Michigan Housing Public Affairs office disseminated information and served as a spokesman for issues related to student housing. The files were collected or created by Alan Levy who was the director of Housing Public Affairs starting in the 1990s. Levy also held previous positions within the Housing Division. Included are topical files on campus issues and student life policies as well as national and international events impacting the campus community.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The bulk of the records were received in May 2008 (Donor No. 8160 ). Additional records were received in 2007 (Donor No. 01355 ).
Periodic additions to the records expected.
The Housing Public Affairs records are open for research, except for one file that is restricted until July 1, 2025.
An alumnus of the University of Michigan, Alan Levy began his career in the University of Michigan Housing Division as an administrator of West Quad dormitory in 1981. By 1991, he had been named Housing Program Director, after which he also served as Housing Public Affairs Director and Housing Division Spokesman. Throughout his tenure with the Housing Division, Levy kept meticulous files of major events and controversies at the university, maintaining particularly thorough documentation of those events with a link to university housing.
These files from Housing Public Affairs, were collected and created by Alan Levy in his roles with the Housing Division, primarily as housing spokesman. Documentation includes files on topics such as alcohol use, capital improvements, crime and safety, diversity in housing, and student deaths. Additionally, the university's response to external events, such as the outbreaks of SARS (Severe Acute Respiratory Syndrome), the September 11 Terrorist Attacks, the Virginia Tech Massacre, and Y2K are also documented. Files on rate changes in university housing during the 1970s, and information of the university's purchase and sale of the Nu Sigma Nu medical fraternity house are also found in these records. The files are arranged into four series: Topical Files, University Housing Rate Changes, Nu Sigma Nu, and Audio-Visual Materials.
Subjects:
Dormitories--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; September 11 Terrorist Attacks, 2001.; University of Michigan. Housing Division.; University of Michigan. Housing Public Affairs.; University of Michigan--Student housing.; University of Michigan--Students--1961-1970.; University of Michigan--Students--1971-1980.; University of Michigan--Students--1981-1990.; University of Michigan--Students--1991-2000.; University of Michigan--Students--2001-2010.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
University of Michigan. Housing Division.; University of Michigan. Housing Public Affairs.; University of Michigan--Student housing.
Genre Terms:
Motion pictures.; Photographs.; Videotapes.
- Topical Files
  The Topical Files document various issues at the University of Michigan, especially as they relate to university housing. They contain correspondence, memos, reports, newspaper clippings, and print-outs of websites. The files are arranged alphabetically by topic. The files offer rich insight into student housing and campus issues spanning the period 1978-2007, with an emphasis on the 1990s and early 2000s.
  - "2002 Staff Organization Development Survey" University Housing (Box 1)
  - "A Brief History and Assessment of University Housing's Cultural Lounges and MPA Program," 2000 (Box 1)
  - "A University Community Approach to Alcohol and Other Drugs," 1992 (Box 1)
  - Affirmative Action 1996-2003, 8 folders (Box 1)
  - Affirmative Action Clippings 1996-2003, 5 folders (Box 1)
  - Alcohol 1992-2005, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Alcohol Clippings 1985-2007 (Box 1)
  - Alcohol and Greek System 1997-2001 (Box 1)
  - Alcohol Media Guides 1998-2004 (Box 1)
  - Alcohol Substance Abuse Education Network (SAEN) 1997-1998 (Box 1)
  - "An Ordinance to Regulate Parking and Traffic and to Regulate the Use and Protection of the Buildings and Property of the Regents of the University of Michigan," 1995 (Box 1)
  - Asian Tsunami 2004 (Box 1)
  - Baker, Jake-Internet Harassment 1995 (Box 1)
  - Bird Flu (Box 1)
  - Black Action Movement (BAM) Conference 1991 (Box 1)
  - "Black Experience and UM Residence Halls, 1968-1977" 1978 (Box 1)
  - Campus Safety circa 1990-2006 (Box 1)
  - Campus-wide Advertising Policy 1992 (Box 1)
  - Capital Improvements and Renewals
    - 1979-1990 (Box 1)
    - 1991-1995 (Box 1)
    - 1996-1998 (Box 2)
    - 1999-2001 (Box 2)
    - 2002-2007 (Box 2)
  - Capital Improvements and Renewals "Strategic Planning Overview: Capital Improvements and Facility Renewal, a Presentation to the Board of Regents," April 1997 (Box 2)
  - Carl Cohen Reading Room Naming Controversy 1999 (Box 2)
  - Child Deaths in Family Housing 1994, 2003 (Box 2)
  - Coca-Cola Boycott 2005-2006 (Box 2)
  - Code of Non-Academic Student Conduct 1980s (Box 2)
  - Code of Non-Academic Student Conduct 1990s (Box 2)
  - Community Relations 1987-2002 (Box 2)
  - Crime Alerts Winter 2002 (Box 2)
  - Crime and Crime Prevention 1987-2003, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Damage Assessment Procedures 1987-2000 (Box 2)
  - Department of Public Safety 1992-2005 (Box 2)
  - Discriminatory Acts 1987-1999, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Discriminatory Acts-clippings 1988-1995 (Box 2)
  - Diversity in Housing 1996-2001 (Box 2)
  - Diversity Resource Forum 1987-1991 (Box 2)
  - East Quad Assault February 2002 (Box 2)
  - East Quad Drug Surveillance 1992 (Box 2)
  - East Quad Elevator Project 1998 (Box 2)
  - East Quad Sexual Assault July 1998 (Box 2)
  - Eastern Michigan University Student Murder December 2006 (Box 2)
  - Elevated Beds Safety Study 2000 (Box 2)
  - Employee Harassment Policy 1988-1989 (Box 2)
  - Facility Renewal and Capital Improvements Program-1991 1996 (Box 2)
  - Facility Staff's Letter on Sexual Orientation February 1993 (Box 2)
  - Fires 1995, 1996, 2004
    - West Quad Fire August, 2000 (Box 2)
  - "From Inclusion to Acceptance: Report of the Task Force on the Campus Climate for Transgender, Bisexual, Lesbian and Gay (TBLG) Faculty, Staff and Students," 2004. (Box 2)
  - Gender Identity and Housing 2000-2006, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Hillary Rodham Clinton Visit 1998 (Box 2)
  - Housing Discriminatory Acts Policy 1988-1993 (Box 2)
  - Housing Division Task Force on Alcohol Report 1983 (Box 3)
  - Housing Security Statistics 1990-2001 (not comprehensive) (Box 3)
  - Hurricane Katrina 2005 (Box 3)
  - International Student Reports 1994-1995, 1996-1997 (Box 3)
  - Kaczynski, Theodore (Box 3)
  - Koernke, Mark-Media coverage (Box 3)
  - Koernke, Mark
    [PR RESTRICTED until July 1 2025; removed to Vault]
  - Luxury Dorms 2006-2007 (Box 3)
  - Markley Hate Speech 1991 (Box 3)
  - Meningitis in Markley 2005 (Box 3)
  - Michigan Union Access Policy 1991-1992 (Box 3)
  - Minority Occupancy Reports 1993-1994, 1994-1995, 1997-1998 (Box 3)
  - Minority Occupancy Analysis 1973-1983, 3 folders (Box 3)
  - Minority Recruitment and Retention Committee 1981-1983, 3 folders (Box 3)
  - Includes evaluations of presentations on African-American student success (folder 2) (Box 3)
  - Minority Unit Planning 1983, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Mold in Residence Halls 2001-2002 (Box 3)
  - Multiculturalism (see also Diversity in Housing) 1989-1995 (Box 3)
  - Multicultural Identity Awareness: Resident Staff Training 1989 (Box 3)
  - "Multivariate Analyses of Student Support for Multiculturalism: The Michigan Study," a report 1993 (Box 3)
  - North Quad Plans 2004-2005 (Box 3)
  - Off-Campus Housing 2006 (Box 3)
  - Orientation Diversity Program 1988-1992 (Box 3)
  - People Acting for Change Together (PACT) 1975 (Box 3)
  - Race and Diversity 1979-1989 (Box 3)
  - Race and Diversity 1990-2004 (Box 3)
  - Race and Diversity--Clippings (Box 3)
  - Religion 1992-2005 (Box 3)
  - Resident Staff Race and Gender Report (Box 4)
    - 1994-1995 (Box 4)
    - 1996-1997 (Box 4)
    - 1997-1998 (Box 4)
  - Residential Life Initiatives (RLI) 2003-2005 (Box 4)
  - "SARS Management Planning, Summary and Samples-September, 2003" A Report (Box 4)
  - "SARS Preparations Summary," A Report-University Housing 2003 (Box 4)
  - SARS 2003
    - Advisory Committee (Box 4)
    - Arrival Management (Box 4)
    - Clippings (Box 4)
    - Communication with Campus (Box 4)
    - Housing SARS Planning Group (Box 4)
    - Quarantine Planning (Box 4)
    - Students from Affected Countries (Box 4)
    - Study Abroad in SARS Countries and Travel Advisories (Box 4)
    - University Health Service Response (Box 4)
  - September 11 Attacks, University Response, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - South Quad Water Leak 2003 (Box 4)
  - South Quad-West Quad Snowball Fight 2007 (Box 4)
  - Student Deaths 1991-2005
    - Courtney Cantor 1998, 3 folders (Box 4)
    - Kenneth Keppen 2005 (Box 4)
    - Katherine Kruse 1991 (Box 4)
    - Sarah Metzger and Celia Zwerdling 1999 (Box 4)
    - Oluwapelumi Odufuye 1994 (Box 4)
    - Kristi Sprecher 2004 (Box 4)
    - Candy Wei 2001 (Box 4)
    - Amanda Yeo 2002 (Box 4)
    - Norhananim Zainol and Teh Nanni Roshema 2003 (Box 4)
  - "University Housing at the University of Michigan," A Report 2000 (Box 4)
  - University Housing Window Safety Study 1999 (Box 4)
  - University Terrace 1987-1994 (Box 4)
  - Vice President of Student Affairs South Quad Stay February 1992 (Box 4)
  - Violations of Community Living Standards 2001-2003 (Box 4)
  - Violations of Community Living Standards 2003-2006 (Box 4)
  - Viral Gastroenteritis February 2004, 3 folders (Box 4)
  - Virginia Tech Massacre (Box 4)
  - West Quad Flood April 2006 (Box 4)
  - Y2K Response, 3 folders (Box 4)
  - Year of Humanities and Arts (1997-1998) (Box 4)
- University Housing Rate Changes
  The series University Housing Rate Changes contains information and deliberations by the Apartment Rate Committee and the Family Housing Rate Study Committees about rate changes in University Housing from 1970 to 1982.
  - Family Housing Rate Study Committee (Box 5)
    - 1972-1973 (Box 5)
    - 1973-1974 (Box 5)
    - 1975-1976 (Box 5)
    - 1976-1977 (Box 5)
    - 1977-1978 (Box 5)
    - 1978-1979, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - 1979-1980, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - 1980-1981 (includes meeting minutes) (Box 5)
  - Apartment Rate Committee
    - 1970-1971 (Box 5)
    - 1971-1972 (Box 5)
    - Minority Report 1970-1971 (Box 5)
  - Residence Hall Occupancy Reports 1979-1985 (Box 5)
- Nu Sigma Nu House (1912 Geddes) Purchase
  The Nu Sigma Nu series documents the interactions between the medical fraternity Nu Sigma Nu and the Housing Division, particularly the purchase and sale by the university of the Nu Sigma Nu house at 1912 Geddes. The files are arranged chronologically.
  - 1960s, 4 folders (Box 5)
  - 1970s (Box 5)
  - 1980s (Box 5)
  - 1990s (Box 5)
  - 2000-2004, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Floor Plans (Box 5)
- Audio-Visual Materials
  The Audio-Visual Materials contains videotapes and a film created to introduce prospective students and their parents to life at Michigan and their housing options. The undated film "Living at Michigan" is in 16mm format.
  - Parent Orientation Slide Show undated, VHS tape (Box 6)
  - Off-Campus Housing Summit 2003 (VHS tape) (Box 6)
  - Substance-Free Housing TV Clips 1991-1996, VHS tape (Box 6)
  - Parent Orientation Show 1992, VHS tape (Box 6)
  - Welcome to Family Housing at the University of Michigan 1995, VHS tape
  - Parent Orientation Video 1992, U-matic cassette (Box 6)
  - Living at Michigan undated, 35mm film (Box 6)